<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short and briefe summe of saving knowledge consisting of the creed, ten Commandements, Lords prayer and the sacraments. And is made profitable introduction to the larger art of divinitie, composed by the methodicall tables of A.R. and published by I.Y.</title>
            <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1698:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short and briefe summe of saving knowledge consisting of the creed, ten Commandements, Lords prayer and the sacraments. And is made profitable introduction to the larger art of divinitie, composed by the methodicall tables of A.R. and published by I.Y.</title>
                  <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Fulke Clifton, and are to be sold under St. Margrets Church on Fish-streete hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.Y. = John Yates.</note>
                  <note>A catechism.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT AND BRIEFE SVMME Of ſaving Knowledge; Conſiſting of the Creed, ten Commandements, <hi>Lords Prayer, and the Sacraments.</hi> And is made as a profitable Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to the larger Art of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, compoſed by the metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall Tables of <hi>A. R.</hi> and publiſhed by <hi>I. Y.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 PETER 2.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>As new borne babes deſire the ſincere milke of the Word, that yee may grow thereby.</p>
               <p>Not as babes ever ſucking, never batling.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Fulke Clifton,</hi> and are to be ſold vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Margrets</hi> Church on Fiſh-ſtreete hill. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Religious Student of the Art <hi>of Well-liuing.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou mayeſt (Chriſtian Reader) after thou haſt ſtudied, and well pervſed this ſhort Summe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, purchaſe to thy ſelfe (if thy purſe and paines will ſuffer thee) the learned Theologie and Divinitie of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man of God M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Alexander Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne.</hi> This may be for preparation, that will bee for further perfection. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Leaving the beginning of Chriſt, let vs goe on to perfection.</hi> It is a ſhame ever to be vnder the ſpoone, and never to vſe the knife. <hi>Ever learning, and never to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7. Yet ſoft and ſure is the beſt pace. Leap-Chriſtians (like horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſers
<pb facs="tcp:14342:3"/>Iades) gallop into profeſſion, and then ſhamefully tyre and giue in. It lames a weake Childe to vſe limmes too ſoone, and over-much forwardnes argues no perpetuitie. Learne we then firſt to goe eaſily, and afterwards to runne with ſpeed the wayes of Gods Commandements.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:3"/>
            <head>The Catechiſme defined, and diſtributed.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>Of Faith in God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat inducements to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are prefixed before your Catechiſme?</p>
               <p>Anſwere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foure, firſt, the giuing vp of my name to God in Baptiſme, and that in the dreadfull name of Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. Secondly, that being not able to giue it vp my ſelfe, it was done by others, according to the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cuſtome of the Church, ever conioyning <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and <hi>Confeſſion</hi> together,</hi> Math. 3.6. Aug. Epiſt. 24. <hi>Papiſts would haue it to contract ſpirituall kindred, but ſurely it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth honeſt loue amongſt neighbours. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They that gaue it vp for me, did promiſe
<pb facs="tcp:14342:4"/>in my name that I ſhould liue according to Religion. Fourthly, I beleeue in conſcience that I am bound to performe what they haue promiſed. Thus becauſe I am Gods, and bound to him by ſureties, vowes, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Conſcience it ſelfe, It is my dutie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nowe come to yeeres of diſcretion, to learne to beleeue in him, and obey him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What then is Religion?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is the <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of the truth which is after godlineſſe,</hi> Tit. 1.1.</p>
               <p>Q. What are the parts?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Workes;</hi> the ſumme of the one is contained in the Creed: of the other in the ten Commandements, Lords prayer, and the Sacraments.</hi> Tit. 3.8.</p>
               <p>Q. What is Faith?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>A confidence in God, grounded vpon knowledge,</hi> Ioh. 16.30. <hi>Wee know and by this beleeue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How is Faith grounded vpon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>In regard of <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church:</hi> the maker of the Couenant, and the people with whom it is made.</hi> Ier. 31.33.</p>
               <p>Q. How in reſpect of God?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>As we beleeue in <hi>one God,</hi> and <hi>three perſons</hi> for our happineſſe,</hi> Ioh. 14.1.</p>
               <p>Q. How in one God?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:4"/>
               <p>A. <hi>In reſpect of <hi>nature,</hi> eſſence, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Deut. 4.35.</p>
               <p>Q. How in three perſons?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Three in regard of <hi>divine revelation,</hi> or reall reſpects in that one moſt pure eſſence</hi> Mat. 28.19.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the eſſence?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That whereby God is of himſelfe, the moſt abſolute and firſt <hi>being,</hi>
                  </hi> Iſa. 41.4.</p>
               <p>Q. What is a perſon?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That one pure pure God with the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of a Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1. Ioh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>Q. Doth the relation adde any thing to the eſſence?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Nothing but reſpect or relation, as <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull hath the ſame nature as he is a Father and as he is a man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the Relation?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is either to <hi>ſend</hi> or be <hi>ſent,</hi> and both theſe are done either by nature, or counſell.</hi> Ioh. 15.26. <hi>the ſpirit proceedeth from the father and ſonne by nature, and is ſent to vs by counſell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Is there no other relation?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes, either to <hi>beget</hi> or be <hi>begotten,</hi> and the father begets his onely ſonne by nature, and the reſt of his children by counſell.</hi> Heb.
<pb facs="tcp:14342:5"/>1.3. Iam. 1.18. <hi>A man hauing the relation of a father is ſaid to beget children by nature or counſell, as adopted children are freely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, not of the bodie but the will.</hi> Iam. 1.18. <hi>
                     <hi>Of his owne will begat he vs,</hi> not ſo his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne, who is as naturall to his Father, as burning to the fire, and as <hi>Iſaac</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What then is the firſt perſon?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>God the father, who by <hi>nature</hi> begets his ſonne, &amp; by his <hi>counſell</hi> creats the world.</hi> Heb. 1.2.5.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the propertie of the Father?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>To <hi>beget,</hi> and not to be begotten.</hi> Ioh. 3.16.</p>
               <p>Q. What is his manner of ſubſiſting?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>To be the <hi>firſt perſon;</hi> for the begetter is before the begotten, and yet being Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues they are together in nature, for no man is a father before he haue a ſonne, though in order the father be firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the fathers worke?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Creation;</hi> for, I beleeue in him as maker of heauen and earth: and the reaſon is becauſe he is the firſt perſon, to whom the firſt worke belongs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is Creation?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>A worke of the Father, who of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his ſonne and ſpirit, makes the <hi>world</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14342:5"/>of nothing exceeding Good.</hi> Gen. 1.31. Heb. 1.3.</p>
               <p>Q. What is giuen to the Father in reſpect of Creation?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Almightie power;</hi> for the Father in himſelfe is pure act, which act is power as it may be felt of his creatures, which are in power to be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is omnipotencie?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is that whereby the Father is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doe all that he doth, and more then hée doth, if it contradict not his owne nature or the nature of things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How is Creation devided?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Into <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>earth.</hi>
                  </hi> Gen. 1.1.</p>
               <p>Q. What meane you by heauen?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The third heauen, with the Angels, both which were made perfect in the very firſt beginning of time.</hi> Gen. 1.1.</p>
               <p>Q. What meane you by earth?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>All that <hi>matter</hi> which was cloſed and compaſſed about with the third heauen, and was made at the ſame inſtant with it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite and keepe out vacuitie, or emptineſſe, and fill vp the whole compaſſe of it, otherwiſe the parts of themſelues would haue fallen to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to haue kept out that enemy of nature.</hi> Gen. 1.1.</p>
               <p>Q. Are wee to vnderſtand no more by
<pb facs="tcp:14342:6"/>earth then that firſt matter?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Yes, wee are to vnderſtand the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of it into the foure elements, <hi>fire, ayre, water,</hi> and <hi>earth;</hi> as likewiſe the filling of if and them with <hi>inhabitants,</hi> beth aboue and below: as alſo the <hi>providence</hi> of the Father in preſeruing &amp; gouerning of them all to their ends and vſee: for the Father carries the worke according to his proper manner of working, vntill wée come to Redemption, and there the ſonne takes it vpon him in a peculiar manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſecond perſon?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The ſonne, who is begotten of the Father by nature, and by counſell, redeemes <hi>mankind.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the relatiue propertie of the ſonne?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>To be <hi>begotten.</hi>
                  </hi> Heb. 1.5.</p>
               <p>Q. What is his manner of ſubſiſting?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>To be the <hi>ſecond perſon</hi> in order, not in nature, for the begotten in relation is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally as ſoone as the begetter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is his worke?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Redemption.</hi> Epheſ 1.7.</p>
               <p>Q. What is Redemption?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is a <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> made to the Iuſtice of God the Father for Man by a Redéemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Who is the Redeemer?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:6"/>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> his onely ſonne our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Why call you him Ieſus?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Becauſe he is a <hi>Saviour of his people from their ſianes.</hi>
                  </hi> Math. 1.21.</p>
               <p>Q. Why Chriſt?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>In regard of his <hi>offices,</hi> as he is anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet.</hi>
                  </hi> Pſal. 45.7. Luke 4.18. Act. 4.27. <hi>and</hi> 10.38.</p>
               <p>Q. Why his onely Sonne?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Becauſe the Father can haue no more ſonnes <hi>by nature</hi> but one</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Why our Lord?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>By the right of <hi>Redemption.</hi>
                  </hi> Rom. 14, 9.</p>
               <p>Q. How is our Redemption wrought?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>By the <hi>humiliation</hi> and <hi>exaltation</hi> of the Sonne of God.</hi> Luke 24.26.</p>
               <p>Q. What be the ſeuerall degrees of his humiliation?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Seven,</hi> there be ſome others left out of the Créed; but theſe expreſſed are the principall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What are they?</p>
               <p>A. 1. <hi>His <hi>conception,</hi>
                  </hi> 2. <hi>his <hi>nativitie,</hi>
                  </hi> 3. <hi>his <hi>paſſion</hi> vnder</hi> Pilate, 4. <hi>his <hi>crucifying,</hi>
                  </hi> 5. <hi>his <hi>dying,</hi>
                  </hi> 6. <hi>his <hi>buriall,</hi>
                  </hi> 7. <hi>his <hi>deſcent</hi> into hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What are meant by all theſe?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That Chriſt muſt not onely ſatisfie in generall, but that he muſt paſſe through the
<pb facs="tcp:14342:7"/>
                     <hi>degrees</hi> of our ſorrowes, and beare our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi> Iſa. 53.4.5.</p>
               <p>Q. What be the ſeuerall degrees of his exaltation?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Foure,</hi> which are his <hi>Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, Sitting at Gods right hand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to Iudgement.</hi> As in his humiliation he tooke our receits, and taſted the bitter poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for vs, ſo all phyſicke being ended of that kinde, hee giues vs his receits of <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  </hi> Ephe. 1.7. <hi>Iuſtification.</hi> Rom. 3.24. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation.</hi> Coloſ. 1.20. <hi>Sanctification.</hi> 1. Pet. 1.2. <hi>Entrance into glory.</hi> Heb. 10.19. <hi>theſe are Cordials for vs, and for him after all his penall receits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the third perſon?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The holy Spirit. who <hi>by nature</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Father, and the Sonne, and <hi>by counſell</hi> applyeth Chriſt to the Church and euery member thereof, the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt perſon elects, the Sonne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemes, and the Spirit ſanctifies.</hi> Ioh. 14.26. <hi>and</hi> 15.26. Rom. 8.16. 1. Cor. 2.12. Iohn 3.5. 2. Cor. 1.21. Rom. 8.23.</p>
               <p>Q. What is his Relatiue propertie?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>To <hi>Proceede.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding begets an Image of it ſelfe, and loues it, and ſo from the beſt vnderſtanding to the beſt obiect of it, proceedes a mutuall loue. The beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:14342:7"/>loues the begotten, and the begotten loues the begetter, and their loue is equall to themſelues, and proceedes from them both, and to vs. The <hi>will</hi> of the Father, by the <hi>wiſedome</hi> of his Sonne, and <hi>power</hi> of his good Spirit is ſayd to doe all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is his manner of ſubſiſting?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>To be the <hi>third perſon</hi> in order, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from two, hee muſt needes bee the third, and yet in nature as ſoone as either of them; for the louers and the loued, are Relatiues, and therefore together in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is his worke?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Application,</hi> or Sanctification.</hi> Ephe. 5.26.27. <hi>The Sonne hauing prepared the remedy, leaues it to be applyed by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> Iohn 16.7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the faith of the</hi> Church.</head>
               <head type="sub">Hitherto of Faith in God.</head>
               <p>Q. What is the faith of the Church?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Whereby beleeuing in God, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beleeue, that wee are of the <hi>Church,</hi> and made partakers of all good things promiſed vnto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:8"/>
               <p>Q. What is the Church?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>The number of all thoſe that are apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Chriſt by the ſpirit:</hi> New as this Vnion is made by Faith, it is called the <hi>militant</hi> Church, as by viſion, the <hi>triumphant.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Why is it called holy?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Becauſe it is an holy Societie of <hi>Saints</hi> in regard of the Spirits worke.</hi> 1. Pet. 2.9. Reu. 11.2. <hi>and</hi> 21.29.</p>
               <p>Q. Why Catholicke?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Becauſe it is <hi>vniuerſall</hi> in reſpect of all <hi>times, perſons,</hi> and <hi>places,</hi> a familie both in heauen and earth.</hi> Math. 26.13. Epheſ. 3.15. 1. Iohn 2.1. Reue. 7.9.</p>
               <p>Q. What are the benefits God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Two in this life, as the <hi>communion</hi> of Saints, and <hi>remiſſion</hi> of ſinnes: and two in the life to come, as the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of the body, and <hi>life euerlaſting,</hi>
                  </hi> Lam. 3.23. Pſal. 68.19. Col. 1.5. <hi>and</hi> 3.3.4. 1. Iohn 3.2.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the communion of Saints?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is our communicating with God, and the godly both in <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> or that fellowſhip that wee haue with Chriſt our head, and all his members.</hi> Pſal. 16.5. <hi>and</hi> 73.26. Iſay 55.1. Act. 4.32. Gal. 6.10. Epheſ. 4.3.4.5.6. Heb. 10.24. Phil. 2.1.2. 1. Cor. 10.16. Reue. 3.18. <hi>and</hi> 6.20.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:8"/>
               <p>Q. What is remiſſion of Sinne?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is a worke of mercy, whereby the <hi>Father</hi> being offended, and reconciled by his <hi>Sonne,</hi> doth witneſſe to our conſciences by his <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> that all our ſinnes are diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and that wee are graciouſly receiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into his fauour.</hi> Iob 33.27.28. 1. King 8.47. Hoſ. 14.2. Iſa. 33.24. <hi>and</hi> 62.11. <hi>God in forgiuing our ſinnes doth both couer and cure them.</hi> 1. Iohn 1.9.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the reſurrection of the body?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is a ſtanding vp from the dead, by the power of <hi>Chriſts reſurrection,</hi> whereby our corruptible bodies are made incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and filled with all glory and erceliency</hi> Iob 19.25.26. Iohn 5.28. Act. 3.19. 1. Cor. 15.42.43. 2. Cor. 5.1. Heb. 11.35.</p>
               <p>Q. What meane you by life Euerlaſting?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That moſt bleſſed and happy eſtate in which all the <hi>Elect</hi> of God ſhall reigne with Chriſt their head in the thirde heauen, after this life, and after the day of iudgement, and that both in body and ſoule for euer and euer.</hi> Pſal 16.11. Iſa. 64.4. Iohn 17.20.21. 1. Cor. 2.9. <hi>and</hi> 13.12 <hi>and</hi> 15.28. 2 Cor. 12.4. Phil. 3.21. Reue. 21.22. <hi>and</hi> 22.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of good workes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Hitherto of <hi>faith,</hi> what are the <hi>workes</hi> of Faith?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That <hi>ready act</hi> of Faith to doe as we are bidden.</hi> Rom. 6.16.1. Sam. 12.25. Iam. 2.14 17. Iohn 14.15.1. Theſſ. 1.3. Tit. 3.1.8.</p>
               <p>Q. How are theſe workes deuided?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>They are either our <hi>walking</hi> with God, or <hi>conferring</hi> with him, or <hi>receiuing</hi> from him.</hi> 2. Cor. 7.1. Phil. 1.6. 2. Theſſ. 1.11. heb. 6.17.18. <hi>Faith bids the cleanſed, goe away and ſinne no more, but walke after the Spirit, it prouokes to prayer, and giues vs full confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Gods loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is our walking with God?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is our due <hi>obſeruation</hi> of his lawes in all our wayes.</hi> Pſal. 119.6.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the law of God?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The <hi>rule</hi> that God hath preſcribed vs, for the holy performance of all our actions.</hi> Iſa. 8.20. Rom. 2.15. <hi>and</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>Q. How is the law diſtributed?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is either concerning the <hi>worſhip</hi> of God, or <hi>loue</hi> of our neighbour.</hi> Marke 12.29.30.31.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:9"/>
               <p>Q. What is the firſt Commandement, concerning the worſhip of God?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods before my face.</hi> Gen. 39.9. Iob 31.23.24. Pſal. I 12.1. Pro. 3.5. Iſay 8.13. <hi>and</hi> 51.12. Haback. 1.16. Luke 12.45. Phil. 3.19. Coloſ. 3.5.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme of this precept?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The hauing of the <hi>true God,</hi> and him alone, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the whole man, in the beſt of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſecond Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Image, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 20.4.5.6. Pſal, 44.21. and 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 35.39. Deut. 4.12. Iſay 42.2. Hoſ. 14.8. Hab. 2.18. Math, 15.9.1. Iohn. 5.21.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the Summe heereof?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That wee worſhip God with his <hi>owne worſhip,</hi> and not our owne deuiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the third Commandement?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, &amp;c.</hi> Deut. 38.58. Pſal. 5.16.17. Dan. 4.34. Math. 6.9. Rom. 11.33. 1. Tim. 6.1.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme thereof?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Due <hi>reuerence</hi> to be ſhewed in the worſhip of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:10"/>
               <p>A. <hi>Remember thou keepe holy the Sabboth day, &amp;c.</hi> Neh. 13.15. to 22. Exod. 20.8.9.10.11. Iſa. 58.13. Ier. 17.27. Rev. 1.10.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme of this law?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>All <hi>diligence</hi> in publique Prayer to God, and in learning the will of God, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vpon his owne day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER IIII. <hi>Of Charitie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hitherto of</hi> holineſſe <hi>in the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is that <hi>iuſtice</hi> that we owe to our neighbour?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That wee doe to him, as wee would hee ſhould doe to vs.</hi> Mark. 12.31.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the firſt Commandement of this Table?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Honour thy father and mother, &amp;c.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 20.12.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme thereof?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Due reſpect to our <hi>ſuperiours, infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,</hi> and <hi>equalls,</hi> to honour all according to their place and degree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſecond precept?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> Exod. 20.13.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:10"/>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme of it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Preſervation</hi> of life, as farre as may ſtand with the good of the Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the third Commandement?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</hi> Exod. 20.14.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme of it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Chaſtitie,</hi> both inward and outward, in affection and action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the fourth Commandement?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi> Exod. 20.15.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme of it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and equitie, a vertue that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily giues euery man his owne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the fift Commandement?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 20.16.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme thereof?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Truth,</hi> and our teſtimony thereunto as often as it ſhall lawfully bee required.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſixt Commandement?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet,</hi> Exod. 20.17.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the ſumme thereof?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Contentment,</hi> and <hi>reſiſtance</hi> againſt all concupiſcence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:11"/>
               <head>CHAPTER V. <hi>Of Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Hitherto of the Law.</head>
               <p>Q. What is Prayer.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is a</hi> moving <hi>of God the Father in the name of his Sonne, by the power of his ſpirit, with things agreeable to his will.</hi> Rom. 8.27. Ioh. 16.33.</p>
               <p>Q. Where is the ſumme of this contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>In the <hi>Lords Prayer.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How is that devided?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Into a <hi>preface,</hi> the <hi>petitions,</hi> and the <hi>concluſion.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the Preface?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is the <hi>preparation</hi> of the heart in comming to God; for as wee are to come with boldneſſe, ſo muſt wee alſo come with reverence of his Maieſtie that filleth the heauens,</hi> Pſal. 26.6. <hi>and</hi> 115.3. Eccl. 5.1. Iſa. 66.1. Luk. 15.18.</p>
               <p>Q. What are the words?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Our father which art in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How are the petitions devided?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>They either concerne <hi>God,</hi> or our <hi>ſelues.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:11"/>
               <p>Q. How many concerne God?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How are they devided?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>They either concerne his <hi>Glory,</hi> or the <hi>meanes</hi> of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Which is the petition concerning his Glory?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Hallowed be thy name, Where wée de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that God in his nature, attributes, word, and workes, may be ſanctified by vs,</hi>
                  </hi> Lev. 10.3. Ezek. 38.23. Act. 12.23.</p>
               <p>Q. What are the petitions concerning the meanes of his Glory?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Two. The comming of his <hi>kingdome,</hi> and the doing of his <hi>will.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is meant by thy Kingdome come?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That the <hi>kingdome</hi> of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, both by the inward working of his Spirit, and alſo by the outward meanes, may be enlarged daily, vntill it be perfected at the comming of Chriſt to Iudgement.</hi> Pſal. 122.6. Iſa. 62.7. Rom. 14.17. 2 Theſ. 3.1. 2 Tim. 4.8. Rev. 22.20.</p>
               <p>Q. What is meant by the doing of Gods will vpon earth, as it is done in heauen.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That all <hi>obedience</hi> be giuen to God in the moſt holy and heauenly manner,</hi> Pſal. 86 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>and</hi> 119.36. Mal. 1.6. Act. 24.16.
<pb facs="tcp:14342:12"/>Rom. 8.29. 1 Theſ. 4.3. <hi>And for wants eract performance daily prayer for parden, with a complaining of our wants.</hi> Pſal. 143.2. Rom. 7.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VI. <hi>Of requeſts for our ſelues.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Hitherto of bleſſings concerning our ſanctification of Gods name, comming of his kingdome, and performance of his will.</head>
               <p>Q. What bleſſings concerne our ſelues?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Either ſuch as concerne <hi>this life, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> better;</hi> the bodie, or the ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the petition for this life?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The giuing of vs our <hi>daily bread,</hi> that is, that God would prouide for vs all things conuenient for this life, walking faithfully in our vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and in all things ſubmitting to his heauenly will, and good pleaſure.</hi> Pſal. 37.5. Prov. 10.22. <hi>and</hi> 16.3. <hi>and</hi> 30.8. Hag. 1.6. 1. Tim. 6.8.</p>
               <p>Q. What are the petitions for a better life?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>In regard of the <hi>preſent,</hi> forgiueneſſe of ſinne, and for <hi>future</hi> deliuerance out of all
<pb facs="tcp:14342:12"/>temptations that may any wayes draw vs to ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What meane you by the firſt?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>That all our ſinnes may be forgiuen, and neuer laid to our charge, either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denine vs here, or to confound vs hereafter, and that moſt freely in Ieſus Chriſt, and as we heartily forgiue them that haue offended vs, wherewith goeth an <hi>humble confeſſion</hi> of them to God,</hi> Pſal. 40.12. Luke 11.4. 1 Ioh. 1.9. <hi>
                     <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>deprecation</hi> muſt goe together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What meane you by the ſecond?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The not leading or leauing of vs in temptation, but his moſt gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull deliuerance of vs out of them all; and in this requeſt, we either lament our eſtate to God, or complaine of the wicked who mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt vs.</hi> Deut. 8.2. <hi>and</hi> 13.3. 2 Chron. 32.31. Pſal. 13.2. <hi>and</hi> 55.2.3.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Hitherto of Petition.</head>
                  <p>Q. What is thankeſgiuing?</p>
                  <p>A. <hi>A <hi>gratefull acknowledgment</hi> of all the benefits of God, and aſcribing vnto him do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miuion, power, and glory, for euer and euer, Amen. And this is the ſweet concluding of all our Prayers.</hi> 1 Chron. 29.11. Pſal. 29.2.9.
<pb facs="tcp:14342:13"/>2 Cor. 1.20. Phil. 4.6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER VII. <hi>Of Sacraments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Now wee come to the celebrating of a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> what then is it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>It is a Seale of righteouſneſſe by faith.</hi> Rom. 4.11.</p>
               <p>Q. What are the kinds?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Two, <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi>
                  </hi> Mat. 26.26. <hi>and</hi> 28.19. Gen. 17.11.12. Rom. 4.11. 1 Cor. 10.1.2 3.4</p>
               <p>Q. What is Baptiſme?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>A Sacrament of our <hi>entrance</hi> into Chriſtianitie, or of our ingrafling into Chriſt.</hi> Act. 8.12.38.</p>
               <p>Q. What is the outward ſigne?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Water, with the ſprinkling of it in the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is ſignified by it?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>The waſhing away of our ſinnes and preſenting of vs holy to God the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. What is the Lords Supper?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>A Sacrament of our <hi>continuance</hi> in Chriſtianitie, or our dayly growing vp with Chriſt,</hi> 1. Cor. 11.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:14342:13"/>
               <head>This memorable <hi>Banquet,</hi> propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the <hi>outward Elements and inward Graces.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. How doe the outwarde Elementes teach the outward man?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Either in <hi>themſelues</hi> or <hi>their vſes.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in themſelues?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Both for <hi>ſubstance</hi> and <hi>qualitic,</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How for ſubſtance?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>As the <hi>bread</hi> is the ſtaffe of life and as the <hi>wine</hi> glads the heart of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in their qualities?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>As they are <hi>common</hi> and <hi>ſenſible,</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to the <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>eare, feeling, ſmelling, taſting.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in their vſe?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Either as they are handled by the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi> or by the <hi>receiuers.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How by the Miniſter?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> in ſetting them apart. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in bleſſing of them. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in breaking of the bread, and powring forth of the wine, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> in deliuering them to the Cont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How by the receiuers?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Firſt, by <hi>taking</hi> the bread and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:14342:14"/>the wine. Secondly, by <hi>digeſting</hi> of them: firſt in the ſtomacke, then in the liuer; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in euery part, whereby they are made powerfull to humane duties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How doth all this teach the inward man in reſpect of grace?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>In proportioning them to Chriſt, both in <hi>himſelfe</hi> and in his <hi>vſe.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in himſelfe.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Both in his <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>qualitie.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in his nature?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>As his <hi>body</hi> is the bread of life where of whoſoeuer taſteth ſhall neuer hunger, and his <hi>blood</hi> is drinke indeede, that for euer makes glad the heart and ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in the qualitie?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>As his body and bloud were <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> with ours in all things ſinne onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and that he is made <hi>ſenſible</hi> both to the eare bored by the Spirit, the eye annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with eye-ſalue, and to the feeling of the ſanctified affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alſo to the ſmelling of ioy, and taſting of the hungry ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How in the vſe?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Either as hee is appointed of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or receiued of <hi>vs.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. How of God?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> as hee is called to this worke. <hi>Secondly,</hi> indued with grace. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> as
<pb facs="tcp:14342:14"/>his body is crucified for vs, and his bloode poured out for the waſhing of our wounds. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> as hee is deliuered and giuen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery beleeuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How receiued of vs?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Firſt, he is taken by the <hi>hand of faith,</hi> and his body is fed on by <hi>meditation,</hi> and his blood ſpiritually drunken to waſh our ſoules then is hee diſgeſted, firſt in the <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and then in the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections,</hi> and laſtly, diſtributed to euery faculty both of body and ſoule, by which wee are made able to euery good word and worke, which is the happy life of euery Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14342:15"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>HItherto (Induſtrious and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Reader) I haue but brought thee to the top of Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and with this proſpectiue glaſſe, haue giuen thee the general veiw of the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> If thou wilt be pleaſed (with the Spies ſent out by <hi>Moſes</hi>) to enter further, and ſend forth the Scouts of thy Soule, to make larger diſcoueries, thou ſhalt finde the depthes of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue more fully ſounded concerning thy faith in one God three perſons: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou art entred further into the Continents, and haſt coaſted the ſhores plyed vp the frythes, thou ſhalt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the inhabitants of heauen &amp; earth, their qualities, tempers, regiment of life, their dyet, imployment &amp;c. I meane, thou ſhalt finde in ſome good
<pb facs="tcp:14342:16"/>meaſure, how richly, God hath furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the world, in what excellent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he gouerneth it, eſpeciall his great care for thee and thy happineſſe. In eſſence hee is ſimply one, yet hath he made himſelfe many attributes, ſo that what thou canſt not conceiue by one act of vnderſtanding, thou mayeſt the better perceiue by many: Thou ſhalt ſee the perſons delighting themſelues aboue all thinges in thee and thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and accordingly put foorth themſelues in al their works of Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Prouidence, thou ſhalt find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thy duty &amp; debt to God for al his fauors: for if God <hi>ſhed abroad</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5) <hi>his loue in thy heart,</hi> then muſt thou of neceſſitie loue him againe: No man goes to his bed and warmes it with his owne heat, but hee lookes for heat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: So, God reſting in the heart, lookes for loue out of it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. In a word, I ſhall be glad, if by this, and the other, I ſhall make the <hi>Art</hi> ſo eaſie for thee, that thou mayeſt reape thy
<pb facs="tcp:14342:16"/>profit by it. And thus (as by a letter of advertiſment from the coaſt of <hi>Canaan</hi>) I ceaſe thy further trouble, neuer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to pray for thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, as his owne,</hi> IOHN YATES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
